Hello, and welcome back to
another episode with it's Dr.
Dan.
And today we're going to dive further into
the introduction to nuclear chemistry,
specifically looking at half life.
So what this is all about is going
off of what our last video was all
about, which was all the different
types of nuclear radiation.
So whenever you have an unstable
nuclei, let's say like the one here
with all these little protons and
neutrons, It will decay, meaning it
could go through let's say a gamma
radiation where it just releases
energy, maybe it releases a positron,
a beta particle, an alpha particle.
So if you're trying to interested
in balancing those reactions,
refer to my other video.
This one's just on half life.
So when we have radioactive decay.
What exactly is happening?
Well, it takes so much time
for each one of these radio
isotopes to decay and break down.
Now, every time, whenever we have one
of these, it goes through a half life.
So, what the whole idea
of a half life is...
It's whenever we have a radioisotope
and it's the time it takes for it to,
for it to decay by exactly one half
of its original amount, meaning that
if I have, let's say a sample here
and it goes through exactly one half
life, so we'll just say one T one half.
So when that happens, it's
going to decay by half.
So like, as we have on this original
portion here, this is a hundred percent.
Then when it goes through one half
life, it's gonna go down to 50%.
If it goes through a second half life,
it will have 25 percent remaining.
And that will keep going down over time.
It will keep decreasing as we move further
and further and further, decaying by half.
So what kind of problems
could you possibly see?
Let's go through a bunch
of different calculations.
to show how this is going to happen and
we'll even look at what kind of ranges of
values we'll even see for what to expect
when it comes to working with half lives.
Let's take a look.
The first thing is what about the ranges?
So half life values can range from
all kinds of things from minutes
to years to sometimes millions and
billions of years depending on the
actual radioactive process and how
stable or unstable the element is.
Here I just included about four different
examples that we have here, ranging
from carbon 14, which we use to date
historical artifacts that we find
around the world, to things that could
be used more in medical applications
where they last on shorter timescales.
So one thing you might notice is that
they all have different processes such
as beta particles, alpha particles,
positrons, where they could last
everywhere from thousands of years
to as short as just a few minutes.
So we're going to be talking about
all kinds of different scales
and just adding up the values.
So this is for introductory chemistry,
so we're not going to be going
through the exponential uh, equations
that you'll see in things that
are more general chemistry one or
general chemistry two with kinetics.
This is just introductory level examples.
Let's go into the different problems.
With our first example, what we have
here is a 20 mg sample of iodine
131 decays, and it only leaves 2.
5 mg.
How long would this take?
How exactly are we going
to go through this?
Well, the first thing is we have to
remember is that every time we go through
a half life, the mass or the amount is
going to decrease by So, there are a
lot of different little strategies that
we can go through for how to do this.
What we have to remember is
that our original sample is
starting at 20 milligrams.
And what we are going to be
doing is dividing it by half
for every single half life.
So being that we're going from 20 to 2.
5, let's first just
divide our mass in half.
So our first one would go from 20 to
10, our second one would go from 10
to 5, right, 10 divided by 2 is 5.
Then if we take 5 divided
by 2, we will get to 2.
5.
So, how much time exactly passed?
Well, let's take a look.
Every single one of these arrows
represents a half life, so it's in a
certain amount of time that is passing.
So in this particular problem,
a half life is equal to 8 days.
So what exactly occurred?
Well, after the first half life that
is here, this was 8 days exactly, which
as the course of time took place, it
went from 100 percent of our sample and
decayed it down to 50 percent across
the course of one single half life.
Now, once we went to the second half
life, which was another 8 days, so
a total of 16, it went from 10 to 5,
meaning that we now have 25 percent
of our original sample remaining.
Now, when we go through our last and
final half life, we are down to 12.
5%, Which means that this took
a total of 24 days for this to
break down to decompose and go
through this beta decay process.
So these are some of the
ways you can map it out.
You don't have to do all the percents and
all the work all the time, but it just
helps to be able to visualize and see it.
Let's go take a look
at some more examples.
If you start with a hundred
grams of radon, how much sample
would be left after 44 days?
So, and in this problem I also give
you exactly how long the individual
half life is, so we can see that
we have a half life of 11 days.
So what we need to do is map out
exactly how long would this take.
So this one, it could be, you could
do it a slightly different way.
Well, how many half lives
would fit into 44 days?
Well, we can kind of do a
little bit of math here.
If we have 44 days total, and I
divide that by 11 days, it's going
to be about four half lives is
how long this is going to take.
Let's go how that would work, right?
I would first start
once again at 100 grams.
Across the first half life,
it would go down to 50 grams.
The second half life
would go down to 25 grams.
The third half life would go down to 12.
5 grams.
And then the fourth half
life would go down to 6.
25 grams.
Now to show, show our work here,
we can put down our t halves,
just to show that each time this
decayed, this would be changing.
So every time that this happens,
this is going to be making,
going from radon and transforming
into a new element as a result.
And then we can see that it's going
to be releasing alpha particles every
single time that this is happening.
So it's going to be changing.
So this is how much is decaying.
So at the end, you're only
going to have about 6.
25 percent of your 100 gram
sample that is remaining.
So let's take a look at some other
different types of problems that
we could see when we do these.
If we have a sample of 3, 1 hydrogen.
So hydrogen 3.
And that's decaying through, uh,
beta decay, and it only leaves 3.
1 percent of the original sample.
How long would this take?
The half life for this one is 12.
3 years.
How long?
How can we do it?
Well, with this one, we weren't,
we didn't get a starting amount,
but we were given a percent.
So if we know that every half
life decays by half, why don't we
just map out the percents, right?
Just like how we did in the
very beginning of this video.
So if we have 100%...
It would decay down to 50%, which
would then decay down to 25%,
which would then go down to 12.
5%, and that would
further decay down to 6.
25%, which would then go down to 3.
125%, which is approximately
where we want to go.
So how many, how many
times will this change?
Well, we can number it out, right?
We have one, two, three.
for five half lives that this
will have to go through in order
for 3, 1 hydrogen to fully decay.
So, all's we need to do is take our
half life value, right, which is 12.
3 years.
And we would multiply that by
five and we would end up with our
final answer for this particular
problem, which would be 61.
5 years is how long this would take for
it to fully go down to only 3 percent
remaining in this particular problem.
So let's take a look at another example.
You start with 200
milligrams of thallium 207.
So after 100 minutes, there is only 12.
5 milligrams left of your sample.
What is the half life
of this decay process?
So how can we try to figure it out?
Well, we were given how much time there
was, and we also have the starting and
the end masses of this particular problem.
So why don't we try to map
out how much we would have.
So the first thing we would do is,
we are starting with 200 milligrams.
And we are going to be dividing
that mass every single time it goes
through a half life calculation.
So we'll go from 200 to
100 would be the first one.
Then on the next one we
would go from 100 to 50.
Then when we divide it again
we're going to go from 50 to 25.
And then when we go one more time
we're going to go from 25 to 12.
5.
So we are just dividing that
in half with each iteration.
Now, how, how much is our half life?
How do we do this?
Well, if you can see, we have 1, 2, 3,
4, our individual half life intervals.
We know that there was
100 minutes that passed.
So how would we figure out the half life?
Well, we're just going to divide it by the
number of intervals, so 100 divided by 4.
And what that's going to tell
you is our half life, which
in this case is 25 minutes.
It's one half life for
this particular reaction.
Now, if this were to kind of keep
going over and over and over again, you
could keep showing how far this could
truly decay during that time period.
It could keep going.
Now, with half lives, this is a
general idea for most of these
expressions, being that as they decay,
they're going to continuously keep
approaching 0 percent over time.
So you can see this keeps dividing
and dividing and dividing.
Generally, the rule of thumb is
eventually it will get down to just
one particle left or one little amount
left and it will decay to nothing.
It usually takes about 10 cycles
or 10 half lives for that to happen
for it to be over 99 percent gone.
You will see that you can
continue dividing it by two as
long as you want, but this is
how radioactive processes work.
They take time.
They're an unstable,
they're metastable, right?
So as it goes to that radioactive
decay, we will see them continuously
break apart, transform into
new daughter nuclei as it goes.
I hope that it helped by showing how to
do these calculations, and I hope that
it helps you do future homeworks and
to better further your understanding,
whether it's in introductory chemistry
and nursing and radiation technology,
to keep furthering your understanding.
Thank you so much for listening,
and I hope that this video helped.
Please hit that like and subscribe
button if it did, and I hope to
see you around for future videos.
Bye now!